Finding aid to the Elihu Grant papers CA.MS.00397
Smith College Archives
Elihu Grant papers
1873-1948
Smith College Archives
Grant, Elihu, 1873-1942
CA.MS.00397
0.417 linear feet (1 container)
Faculty. Collection contains audio recordings, correspondence, news clippings, photographs, publications and a wedding album documenting the professional and family life of Elihu Grant.
Biographical / Historical
Elihu Grant (1873 - 1942) was born in Stevensville PA to William Thomas and Amanda Lewis Bird Grant. After receiving his undergraduate degree from Boston University in 1898, he remained in Boston to continue his studies at Boston University. In 1899, he married Almy Chase, with whom he had one daughter, Rachel (Class of 1929). Grant received his Ph.D. in 1906 and an S.T.B. in 1907.
During this time he worked as a student pastor in the towns of Wilmington and Revere (1894 - 1901). After being ordained into the Methodist Episcopal ministry in 1900, he was appointed superintendent of the American Friends' Schools in Ram Allah, Jerusalem. He returned to Massachusetts in 1904 to become a pastor in East Saugus.
In 1907, Grant joined the faculty at Smith College as an associate professor of Biblical Literature. Following his work at Smith College, Grant took a professorship at Haverford College in Pennsylvania in 1917 and remained active until his retirement in 1938. While at Haverford, he served as director of the Haverford Graduate School (1923 - 1927), and from 1928 until 1933, he served as director of Haverford American Excavations at Ain Shems (Beth Shemesh).
Grant authored many publications including:
1907 The Peasantry of Palestine: The Life, Manners, and Customs of the Village
1916 The Bible as Literature
1918 Cuneiform Documents in the Smith College Library
1920 The Orient in Biblical Times
1921 The People of Palestine
1922 A New Era In Palestine Exploration
1929 Beth Shemesh (Palestine): Progress of the Haverford Archaeological expedition
1931 Ain Shems Excavations (Palestine) 1928 - 1931, part 1
1932 Ain Shems Excavations (Palestine) 1928 - 1931, part 2
1934 Rumeileh: Being Ain Shems excavations (Palestine), part 3
1936 Ain Shems Excavations (Palestine), part 4
1938 Palestine Today
1938 The Haverford Symposium on Archeology and the Bible
1939 Ain Shems Excavations (Palestine), part 5
1940 Palestine Our Holy Land
Scope and Contents
The collection contains documents pertaining to Elihu Grant's professional and personal life while working at Smith and after including correspondence to his family, especially to his wife Almy Chase Grant and some correspondence to Mrs. Grant from others, including Grace Coolidge. The collection also includes photographs of the family, Grant's publications while working at Smith, sound recordings of his lectures, his obituaries and biographies, and a memorabilia album that documents the Grant's marriage as well as small notes marking the anniversary of their marriage.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source unknown.
photographs; wedding albums; Grant, Almy Chase; Grant, Elihu, 1873 - 1942; Wood, Irving Francis, 1861 - 1934; Haverford College; Smith College. Department of Religion and Biblical Literature; Smith College -- Faculty
- Associate Professor, Biblical Literature, (1907 - 1917), 1917 - 1924 (Box 831, Folder 1)
- biographies, 1928 - 1942 (Box 831, Folder 2)
- American Friends Service Committee, 1932 (Box 831, Folder 3)
- Chase, John F., "Autographs", 1947 - 1948 (Box 831, Folder 4)
- correspondence: Mary Dunham, 1924 (Box 831, Folder 5)
- correspondence: Rachel Grant, 1927 (Box 831, Folder 6)
- correspondence: Franklin S. Chase, 1901 (Box 831, Folder 7)
- correspondence: Borden P. Bonne, 1901 (Box 831, Folder 8)
- correspondence: George Abbott Coe, 1906 (Box 831, Folder 9)
- correspondence: Caspar Rene Gregory, 1903 (Box 831, Folder 10)
- correspondence: Grace Goodhue Coolidge, 1928 (Box 831, Folder 11)
- correspondence: Robert Alexander Stuart Macalister, 1910 (Box 831, Folder 12)
- correspondence: John Punnett Peters, 1907 (Box 831, Folder 13)
- correspondence: L. Clarke Seelye, 1909 (Box 831, Folder 14)
- correspondence: John Heyl Vincent, 1903 (Box 831, Folder 15)
- correspondence: Henry White Warren, 1907 (Box 831, Folder 16)
- correspondence: William Fairfield Warren, 1905 (Box 831, Folder 17)
- correspondence: Elihu Grant, Almy (Chase) Grant, 1897 - 1928 (Box 831, Folder 18)
- correspondence - Mary (Almy) Chase, 1901 - 1902 (Box 831, Folder 19)
- correspondence: "Grandma and Grandpa", 1880 (Box 831, Folder 20)
- photographs, undated (Box 831, Folder 21)
- photographs: Almy (Chase) Grant, undated (Box 831, Folder 22)
- photographs: excavations, 1928 (Box 831, Folder 23)
- publications, "Babylonian Business Documents of the Classical Period", 1919 (Box 831, Folder 24)
- publications, "Cuneiform Documents in the Smith College Library", 1918 (Box 831, Folder 25)
- publications, "Religion in Action Series in Ancient Times", undated (Box 831, Folder 26)
- wedding album, 1899 - 1947 (Box 831, Folder 27)
- audio recordings of various lectures, 1934 (Box 831, Folder 28)